"Preventing and Treating Varicose Veins"
Blood pumps out
through the heart
to the body
through the arteries,
and then returns back
to the heart from the body
through the veins.
Veins contain one-way valves
that direct blood flow
back to our chest.
In our legs, blood flows
from superficial veins
under our skin to deep veins
in our muscles,
and then from distal
to proximal, that is,
from our feet
towards our center.
When our calves contract,
blood is squeezed up
past the knee,
then when
our thigh muscles contract
blood is pushed up
into our torso,
and the valves
prevent backflow.
However, if the valves
in our leg veins fail,
blood flows down and out,
and veins under our skin
can become enlarged
and tortuous.
These so-called varicose veins
affect as many
as 15 percent of men
and 29 percent of women.
Varicose veins are not just
a cosmetic issue.
They can be associated with
feelings of pain, heaviness,
and itchiness.
Compression stockings
were traditionally
the standard therapy
for management of symptoms,
but over the last decade,
the lack of evidence
for compression efficacy
combined with the development
of minimally invasive
endovenous ablation techniques
has shifted
treatment recommendations.
Under local anesthesia,
a vascular surgeon
or interventional radiologist
makes a small incision
and under ultrasound guidance
threads a catheter
into the varicose vein
and then uses laser
or high-intensity radio waves
to cauterize (burn) the vein
from the inside out,
closing it off.
(The body then reroutes blood
through other veins.)
There is a risk of damaging
the surrounding nerves,
which happens
in about 7 percent of cases,
but most nerve damage
is temporary.
Full surgical removal
of varicose veins
has fallen into disfavor,
but based on
a five-year follow-up
of a randomized trial
of treatments
it may still be preferable
to sclerotherapy,
in which a caustic
chemical liquid or foam
is injected straight into a vein
to scar it closed.
You’ll note that
none of these treatments
actually treats
the underlying cause.
What can we do
to prevent varicose veins
in the first place?
Risk factors
for varicose veins
include chronically increased
intra-abdominal pressure
due to obesity, pregnancy,
or chronic constipation,
along with being a woman,
and prolonged standing.
In fact, part of the reason
women are at higher risk
may be because they are
more likely to be in jobs
requiring prolonged standing.
(Those who do need
to stand all day
can take solace
in the fact
that standing more
on a regular basis
is associated with
a decreased risk
of obesity
and premature death.)
Another reason varicose veins
are more common in women
is pregnancy, with more kids
associated with more risk.
(Again, hopefully, worth it!)
Though obesity appears
to triple the risk,
that still can’t account for
the extraordinary disparity
between the rates
in the industrialized world
versus the developing world,
particularly rural Africa.
In Uganda, for example,
a survey found
only six individual cases
of varicose veins
out of 5,000 adults.
Perhaps Africans had more than
50 times fewer varicose veins
for the same reason they had
50 times less heart disease,
up to 50 times
less colon cancer,
and up to
more than 50 times less
of other "pressure diseases,"
like diverticulosis,
hiatal hernia, and hemorrhoids.
Because their diet was so packed
with whole plant foods,
rural Africans were among
the only known populations
ever recorded eating
the 100-plus grams of fiber
that is more normal
for our species
(based on coprolites,
prehistoric "paleopoo"
fossilized feces).
There is an epidemic
of constipation
among Western seniors,
but bowel movements
should be effortless.
When we have
to strain at stool,
the pressure may balloon
outpouchings from our colon,
causing diverticulosis,
and force part of our stomach
up through the diaphragm
into our chest cavity,
causing a hiatal hernia.
The increased abdominal pressure
may also back up blood flow
in the veins around the anus,
causing hemorrhoids,
and push blood flow
back into the legs,
causing the valves in the veins
of our legs to fail,
resulting in varicose veins.
The root cause of straining
is the effort needed to pass
unnaturally firm stools,
but we can treat that cause
by eating
enough fiber-containing
whole plant foods
to create stools
so large and soft
that you can pass them
effortlessly.
Given the fiber connection,
it’s no surprise
that Western vegetarians
also have lower rates
of pressure diseases
like diverticulosis,
hemorrhoids,
and varicose veins,
but that may not be
the only reason.
A study of elderly vegetarians
found they also have
a much lower incidence
of varicose veins
under the tongue,
as well as fewer
sublingual bleeding capillaries,
a condition known
as caviar tongue.
Given the dilation of veins
and thinning
of blood vessel walls
characteristic of scurvy,
the researchers suspect
the low rates of varicose veins
in vegetarians
may also have to do with
their greater vitamin C intake.